Guide to the Sarita Daftary-Steel collection of East New York oral histories 2015.011
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Foglio, Paulette and Holtzman, Jordan, 2014 July 17; 2015.011.07
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business -- New York (State) -- Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Whites |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Foglio, Paulette; Fortunoff (Department store); George Gershwin J.H.S. 166 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Holtzman, Jordan; Linden Houses (Housing complex); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Gonzalez, Gladys, 2014 September 12; 2015.011.08
  In the interview, Gladys Gonzalez discusses moving from the Fort Greene neighborhood to the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, life in East New York in the 1960s, establishing community gardens on her block, her school years and race relations at George Gershwin Junior High School, the effect of drugs and crime on the community, and her optimism regarding the future of the neighborhood. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Gonzalez's home in East New York.
  Gladys (Roldan) Gonzalez was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1953. Her father was born in Puerto Rico and her mother (also of Puerto Rican descent) was born in Spain. Gonzalez was one of nine siblings in the family. In 1959, her parents purchased a home and moved their family from the Fort Greene neighborhood to the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. She attended PS 108, George Gershwin Junior High School, JHS 64, and Thomas Jefferson High School. In 1989, Gonzalez cofounded PS 4 Paradise Garden. The garden was established on vacant lots near her home, which were the result of fires in the neighborhood during the 1980s. She married and had two children.
  Ashford Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |x Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community gardens |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; George Gershwin J.H.S. 166 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Gonzalez, Gladys; P.S. 4K Paradise Garden (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. 108 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. K004 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Gonzalez, Luis, 2014 October 23; 2015.011.09
  In the interview, Luis Gonzalez describes moving from Puerto Rico to Brooklyn, living in the Ocean Hill section of the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn (which he refers to as East New York), relationships with Jewish neighbors, working as a youth, race relations and bullying at school, White flight from the neighborhood, the rise of drugs and crime, and his work as a New York City Housing Police Department officer and detective. The interview was conducted remotely by Sarita Daftary-Steel in Brooklyn, New York and Gonzalez in Arecibo, Puerto Rico.
  Luis Gonzalez was born in 1946 in Rio Piedras, Puerto Rico. His family moved to the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1953, before settling in the Ocean Hill section of the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn (which he refers to as East New York) in 1955. He attended PS 87 and East New York Vocational High School, where he specialized in aviation. Gonzalez resided in the area until 1964, when he left to serve in the U.S. Air Force. He returned to New York in 1968 and later worked as a New York City Housing Police Department officer and detective. He moved back to Puerto Rico in 2001.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brownsville (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ocean Hill (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York Vocational High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Gonzalez, Luis; New York City Housing Authority. Police Department; P.S. 87 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Grizer, Mel, 2014 January 1; 2015.011.10
  Mel Grizer was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania in 1938 to Jewish parents. He attended Temple University and earned a graduate degree from the University of Iowa. He moved to the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1967. There he worked for United Community Centers, a local organization founded on principles of racial integration. He became the organization's Director in 1989, and currently serves as Acting President of the Board of Directors. Grizer lives with his wife and children in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In the interview, Mel Grizer describes moving to public housing in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1967, working with United Community Centers (UCC) to promote integration and the difficulties they faced from both the White and Black communities, the leadership and evolution of UCC through the years, White flight and the changing demographics of the neighborhood, the rise of crime and arson in the community, violence in local public schools, and political corruption. The interview was conducted at Grizer's home in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn by Sarita Daftary-Steel.
  Black nationalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political corruption |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Grizer, Mel; Thomas Jefferson Democratic Club (39th district); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United Community Centers, Inc
- Holtzman, Jordan, 2014 July 17; 2015.011.11
  In the interview, Jordan Holtzman describes growing up in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, attending local schools (PS 190, George Gershwin Junior High School, and Thomas Jefferson High School), working with his father, local businesses on New Lots Avenue, integration of the neighborhood, and the Linden Houses. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at PS 99 in Kew Gardens, Queens, New York.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fortunoff (Department store); George Gershwin J.H.S. 166 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Holtzman, Jordan; Linden Houses (Housing complex); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Joseph, Edwina, 2014 October 31; 2015.011.12
  In the interview, Edwina Joseph describes life in the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, where she resided for over forty five years. She discusses being the first Black family to move into the Houses in 1962, relations with her neighbors, White flight from the Houses, and subsequent decline of the quality of life due to the New York City Housing Authority's disregard for residents. She also discusses the schools her children attended and political activism in the neighborhood. The interview was conducted remotely by Sarita Daftary-Steel in Brooklyn, New York and Joseph in Acworth, Georgia.
  Edwina (Greene) Joseph was born in 1940. She moved from the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn to the Linden Houses (in the East New York neighborhood) with her husband and children in 1962, and lived there until 2010. Joseph worked at the Wells Fargo bank international branch on Wall Street for many years. After her retirement, she was active in the East New York Farms! Project as a member of a Community Supported Agriculture program. In 2010 she moved to Acworth, Georgia.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Voter registration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Espada, Frank; Joseph, Edwina; Linden Houses (Housing complex); New York City Housing Authority; United Community Centers, Inc
- Joseph, Edwina, 2014 November 7; 2015.011.13
  In the interview, Edwina Joseph continues to discuss living in the Linden Houses from 1962 to 2010 and the changes she saw over the years, including a decline in police presence, draconian law enforcement when police were present in the area, the adversarial relationship between the Housing Authority and residents, and the general decline in quality of life. The interview was conducted remotely by Sarita Daftary-Steel in Brooklyn, New York and Joseph in Acworth, Georgia.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Joseph, Edwina; Linden Houses (Housing complex); New York (N.Y.). Police Department; New York City Housing Authority
- Malek, Gloria, 2014 May 12; 2015.011.14
  Gloria (Feingold) Malek was born on September 25, 1933 in Brooklyn, New York, to Jewish parents. She lived in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn where she attended school (PS 90, JHS 109, and Thomas Jefferson High School) and raised her family. Starting in 1957 she resided in the Linden Houses, where she lived for seventeen years. After briefly moving to California, she returned to East New York and lived in Starrett City for fourteen years. She was active in political and community organizations, including the Emma Lazarus Federation of Jewish Women's Clubs, the Women's Strike for Peace, East New York Action, and especially the United Community Centers (of which she serves on the Board of Directors). Malek was married and had two children. Following the end of her first marriage she was in a long-term interracial relationship. She remained in East New York until the 1990s, when she moved to the Stuyvesant Town residential development in Manhattan.
  In the interview, Gloria Malek describes growing up in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1930s through 1950s when it was primarily a Jewish community, living in the Linden Houses and its later decline, White flight, her involvement with political activism and the March on Washington, becoming deeply involved with the United Community Centers and integration, race relations at local schools and bullying, crime and being mugged, and her interracial relationship with a Black man. Throughout the interview she speaks about the challenges she and her family faced living in East New York, but also emphasizes her strong desire to live and socialize in racially mixed communities. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Malek's home in the Stuyvesant Town residential development in Manhattan, New York, New York.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Espada, Frank; Linden Houses (Housing complex); Malek, Gloria; Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United Community Centers, Inc
- Montgomery, Isaiah, 2014 June 20; 2015.011.15
  Isaiah Montgomery was born in Smithville, North Carolina, in 1948 to African American parents. He lived with his grandparents in Spartanburg, South Carolina, until the age of six. At that time he moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn to join his parents, who had migrated to New York several years earlier. In 1963 his family bought a home and moved to 548 Hinsdale Street in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, where he attended Franklin K. Lane High School. Montgomery served in the Vietnam War and then spent much of his adult life employed as a corrections officer. He married, had two children, and continues to live in East New York on Newport Street, where he is a member of a community garden and the East New York Farms! Project.
  In the interview, Isaiah Montgomery describes his move from South Carolina to Brooklyn; his parents' work and taking care of his sister as a youth; moving to the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1963; White flight; the rise of crime, arson, and drugs; race conflict at Franklin K. Lane High School; his children's time at South Shore High School and Thomas Jefferson High School; community gardens; and the current development and revitalization of the neighborhood. He also describes his work as a corrections officer in New York City. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Montgomery's home in East New York.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Arson |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community gardens |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Correctional personnel -- New York (State) -- New York; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Hinsdale Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Newport Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin K. Lane High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Montgomery, Isaiah; South Shore High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Piggott, Conrad Wayne, 2015 January 9; 2015.011.16
  In the interview, Conrad Wayne Piggott discusses moving from the Fort Greene Houses to the Boulevard Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, the rural nature of East New York in the 1950s and 1960s, local businesses, playing in the nearby junkyards and wetlands, joining the Marines and serving in the Vietnam War, his affinity for military life, his love of East New York (especially his time as a youth), his father's work as a New York City Transit Police Department detective, his mother's ancestry, teenagers today, corporal punishment, and his interactions with the police. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Brooklyn Public Library's Central Library.
  Biographical notes
  Conrad Wayne Piggott was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1950 to parents of mixed ancestry, including African, German Jewish, Taino, and West Indian. His father was a New York City Transit Police Department detective and his mother was a housewife. Piggott lived in the Fort Greene Houses until 1955, when his family moved to the Boulevard Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, where they remained until 1995. He attended PS 273, George Gershwin Junior High School, and Thomas Jefferson High School. After graduating high school, he joined the Marines and served in the Vietnam War. He remained in military service for much of his life. As of 2015, Piggott is a resident of the Ocean Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Ocean Hill (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Play environments |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Rural conditions |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Veterans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Boulevard Houses (Housing complex); New York (N.Y.). Transit Police Department; Piggott, Conrad Wayne
- Rabinowitz, Richard, 2014 December 8; 2015.011.17
  Richard Rabinowitz was born in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1945. His father was a Jewish American and his mother was a Jewish immigrant who emigrated from Poland in 1928. His family purchased a home on Bradford Street, between Hegeman Avenue and Linden Boulevard, in 1948, and they remained there until 1966 or 1967. He attended PS 213, George Gershwin Junior High School, and Stuyvesant High School. He moved to Massachusetts and attended Harvard University before returning to Brooklyn in the 1980s. Rabinowitz is a public historian and founder of the American History Workshop. He lives in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn with his wife.
  In the interview, Richard Rabinowitz discusses his parents' lives in the 1930s and 1940s, his childhood growing up in the Jewish community of the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s, local businesses and schools, White flight, race relations, and integration. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Rabinowitz's home in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  Bradford Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business -- New York (State) -- Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team); George Gershwin J.H.S. 166 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. 213 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Rabinowitz, Richard
- Richardson, Toni, 2015 February 6; 2015.011.18
  Toni Richardson was born in Manhattan around 1951. Her mother was a Black American who was born in South Carolina and migrated to Brooklyn, and her father was also a descendent of Southern Black Americans. Her family lived in the Amsterdam Houses in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan until 1957, when her father got a job with the New York City Transit Authority and they moved to the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. Richardson attended PS 224, PS 190, and Thomas Jefferson High School. As a teenager, she was an active member of United Community Centers. She lived in Linden Houses until 1972, and her mother continued to live in the Houses until she passed many years later. She now lives in Ossining, New York, and has worked for IBM for much of her life.
  In the interview, Toni Richardson discusses moving from the Amsterdam Houses to the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1957, growing up in the neighborhood and interracial friendships, race relations as a teenager, attending Thomas Jefferson High School, her involvement with United Community Centers, the decline of services in the Linden Houses as the residents shifted from predominantly White to Black, the poor quality of education in local schools, her career as a Black woman at IBM, and systemic racism and its effect on society. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Richardson's home in Ossining, New York.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism in the workplace; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social classes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; International Business Machines Corporation; Linden Houses (Housing complex); Richardson, Toni; Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United Community Centers, Inc
- Smith, Yvonne, 2014 September 8; 2015.011.19
  Yvonne (Nelson) Smith was born in 1944 in the Manhattan neighborhood of Harlem to African American parents. She would later live in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn and Queens. Smith moved with her husband to the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1966, where they resided until 1975. She attended Central Commercial High School and worked for the Federal Treasury Department for thirty two years, while her husband worked for the New York Police Department. She currently lives with her husband and daughter in Rochdale Village, Queens, New York.
  In the interview, Yvonne Smith discusses moving to the Linden Houses in 1966, the decline of the housing development and moving to Rochdale Village in Queens, sending her children to Catholic schools instead of public schools, the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn, the decline of integration in the communities where she has resided, parenting, and racism in society. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Smith's home in Rochdale Village, Queens, New York.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brownsville (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Catholic schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parenting; Racism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Rochdale Village (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Linden Houses (Housing complex); Smith, Yvonne
- Yeancades, Carmen, 2014 August 8; 2015.011.120